howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is thomas bjorkman
co-author of the book the nordic secret
hi jim thank you for having me on your
show
yeah great to have you on here it's very
interesting the book
and i think we have a surprising amount
of things in common and how we're seeing
the world
give you a little bit of background on
thomas he was educated in physics and
macroeconomics and has been an
entrepreneur in a variety of businesses
including financial services media
property development and banking
he's the founder of the x garrett
foundation did i get that even close to
right
x carrot absolutely ear credit
foundation or
as we sometimes use in english the oak
island
foundation okay whose mission is to
facilitate
personal development and social change
it's interesting that we both come from
a background of entrepreneurship
and you know i think corporate america
too to a degree and then became
interested in social transformation
maybe a little bit about your life story
how how did you get the perspective you
have today
um thank you for asking so
first i should clarify my academic
background a little bit yes i've studied
economics but my main academic
background
is actually in mathematics and physics
so i'm a physicist by training and that
explains perhaps a little bit the
perspective i'm i'm coming
from because if you come from a
background of economics then
you tend to take um
the market more or less as a natural
phenomenon and you study that used using
newtonian
mathematics but if you come from a
background of
physics and mathematics then you know
the limitations
of that toolkit and i very early became
interested in
systems science physics and systems
science
generally and how looking at the world
from
a perspective of self-organizing
complex systems actually help you
understand
a a lot of things that can seem
very difficult to to grasp otherwise and
of course the market being being one of
them so i
i view the market as a self-organizing
complex
system but i also look at culture and
human society
as a self-organizing complex system and
actually also which we might come back
to later
i i view our consciousness our mind as
our individual minds as complex
self-organizing systems under
uh life-long development and and
evolution
that makes a lot of sense and in my own
background i did some physics and so i
decided that for various reasons that
career path wasn't for me and went off
in
a different direction but i do believe
that that physics perspective is useful
you know one of the things is most
useful at least in my mind and it sounds
like yours as well
is that the physics lens tends to
allow you to escape from the reification
of these complex systems reification
means
making them too real right the example i
like to use is
money it's an area i've done a very very
deep dive into the history of monetary
systems the nature of monetary systems
many alternative monetary systems
long before bitcoin and one of my pet
peeves
is that most people even pretty
sophisticated thinkers
accept our current form of money as if
it came down from mount
sinai with moses right they don't
realize that it's a whole series of
strange historical accidents and
contingent
short-term adaptations plus the
occasional conspiracy here or there
to have produced a particular frozen
accident in time
and monetary system is hugely important
because it's one of
the social signals that helps the
complex system self-organize
it can be changed a lot i mean it's
plastic it should be under our control
but most people don't understand that i
think the
physics people tend to see that more
easily yeah
because i think for someone with a
natural science background
it might be more easy to see the
difference between
shall we call it a natural
self-organizing
system and a socially constructed
self-organizing system and of course
money and the market is
is a very good example of a socially
constructed
self-organizing system and seeing the
world
as socially constructed is of course a
postmodern
insight but what many post-modern
thinkers and philosophers
get wrong is of course that even though
perhaps
95 of our
human world today is socially
constructed
our whole world is not socially
constructed you also have
natural phenomena and one way to
understand that is to look at the
difference between
oxygen and money so for
us in the modern world as in for us as
individuals
oxygen or air and money are
sort of equally important for us to
survive
we need to breathe to survive and we
also need money to survive
but of course the big difference is that
even if the whole of humanity came
together
and decided that we as humanity do not
want to be dependent
on oxygen any longer we couldn't do
anything about it
but of course if the whole of humanity
or even a nation-state
came together and said as you suggest
that
we don't want to use money or not this
form of money for example
as the major allocation medium for for
our goods in society
we could change that tomorrow like that
so this socially constructed reality
even though it
meets us as individuals as something
very
objective and that we almost look at as
you say
as something that were given by god or
given by nature
we as a collective can actually easily
change it
and then just a final comment on that
and that is that
unfortunately we often
confuse these two cases and you could
say that
it looks like we today somehow believe
that the planetary boundaries
which is a natural phenomenon that the
planetary boundaries
is somehow up for renegotiation
but that the market forces
is something that we just need to obey
whereas of course it's the opposite yeah
it's a perfect example a fine example
and of course the
kobit 19 is another one right absolutely
the virus is going to do what it's going
to do
and yeah you can try to put whatever
spin on the virus
and and try to come up with new
narratives or or whatever or whatever
but the virus is going to kill
those people it's going to kill yup
exactly it's very interesting that this
is a
and this will get into this a lot as we
talk about the book you know that
a mental capacity to see these things is
fundamental
to managing the future which brings us
around to the main topic though i'm sure
we're going to go off topic a lot and i
encourage that we can talk about
anything at any length
we're going to talk today mostly about
the book the nordic secret
which thomas wrote with lenny rachel
anderson an independent futurist and
writer
and so you know she certainly gets a
significant part of the credit for this
book let's not forget her
she should get i should state that she
should get the major credit because she
she actually did the most of the labor
in in
writing this book so that the details
and the research
and all of that is definitely her credit
the concept and their ideas are are
are they should be credited to both of
us okay very good to get that clear
before we jump in let's start with the
word bulldog
if i came up even close to pronouncing
that word a word not very familiar to
our mostly anglo-sphere listeners
except perhaps in the name of the
literary genre buildings roman
in fact bildung is not even in my spell
checker i don't know how many times it
appears in your book but it's a bunch so
maybe you could start by
defining that word yeah it's um
a german word it was used very much by
the
german idealist philosophers
like schiller herder von humboldt
even hegel and you need to understand a
little bit about the
history of ideas and european history of
philosophy to really appreciate the
build on concept and the first thing we
should say is that
these philosophers that wrote at around
the time of the french revolution
and and a bit after they all
reacted against the enlightenment
philosopher's view
of our mind as a rational machine
that was more or less fully developed
when our brain had stopped growing
when we were 18 or 20 or something and
and then it was just functioning
i mean this enlightenment philosopher's
view of our mind very much
rests on on the writings of philosophers
like descartes
or john locke who was famous for talking
about the blank
slate that we are born with a blank
slate
and this guy who liked the metaphor of
our mind as
a machine know these german philosophers
they said that no the
our mind is more like an organic
complex system that is under constant
evolution throughout our
lives and that evolution
of our mind they gave the name bildung
and bildung is the word is something
like
the organic realization of
something it's a formation but it's more
inert formation so it's more than an
organic realization of something and in
this case it's the
organic realization of our consciousness
and of course this is a way of viewing
our mind and our consciousness that is
very very
different from the way we
usually view our mind and consciousness
in
in the modern western world we keep
thinking that our mind
is this sort of rational machine or at
least some sort of computer
uh that is either functioning or not
functioning
but the fact that this is actually an
evolving system that that is very hard
for us to
to grasp but that was the idea behind
building and that was the view of us
as humans and of our mind that
almost all intellectuals and politicians
in the nordic countries had during
the 1800s and they really
tried to implement this understanding of
lifelong consciousness
development in their political thinking
very good we'll get to all that
including a walk through the
philosophers
in a little bit you know right up front
in the book one of the
flags you put in the ground is that the
nordic countries really are
different you present a lot of economic
data
and survey data and a very i thought a
very interesting
graph from the world values survey which
had a y-axis of traditional versus
secular with the secular up and an
x-axis of survival versus
self-expression with self-expression to
the right
could you talk a little bit about how
the nordic countries are different from
your perspective
yeah so um first of all and
we are quite clear about that in in the
book that
we we do not believe in any sort of
scandinavian
exceptionalism we don't think that we
are
so exceptional today and if we were
exceptional at some point we are
certainly
uh starting to lose it in in scandinavia
but what made us very
different and even exceptional was
in the way that all the nordic uh
countries denmark
norway sweden and then a little bit uh
later
uh finland the way we manage
the transition from
the pre-modern society into
modernity and it's easy to forget
but one should remember that at the end
of the
1800s all the scandinavian
countries were the poorest agrarian
non-democratic countries in
europe and for example
in sweden during the last decades of the
1800s
up to 30 percent of the working
population
emigrated to mainly to the u.s
because of just poor living
conditions in in sweden but then just
a few generations later even before
the second world war we were all
amongst the richest the happiest
most stable industrial democracies in
the world and that transition was also
done peacefully
whereas this transition in other
countries were often
accompanied by bloody revolutions and
wars and and other things
and of course we had luck and we had
some resources and we had a lot of
things but one major contributing
uh factor which lena and i
also say has been mainly forgotten also
in the nordic countries
was this very early focus on
the importance of inner personal
development you could say the
development of
certain inner capabilities or or some
inner
skills that are necessary
in a population particularly in times
of rapid societal
change and if if you allow me to go on
just a little bit longer here
i would say that these leading
intellectual and
and politicians in the nordic countries
they saw
the modern world coming they they they
saw the development in
in england and on the continent of the
indus
industrialization and urbanization but
they also knew from these german
philosophers that
in time of rapid social change
it is just so easy for us humans
to want to have an external authority
to put our trust in like
a dogmatic religion or an authoritarian
leader but these politicians they they
did not want to be authoritarian leaders
they were firmly committed
to build democracy and they knew that
the only way to build democracy
is to build it from bottom up so they
wanted
to again build on this idea of lifelong
consciousness development they wanted to
build up a critical
mass of people in the country that
actually had reached
that level of inner maturity
that they have come to this data that
were grounded enough in themselves
to have internalized a moral compass
and was not any longer dependent
on an outside authority and the way that
they did this
was that they actually created what i
sometimes call
jokingly but it's actually quite a good
um
analogy to say that they created retreat
centers
everywhere in scandinavia so at the turn
of the last century year 1900
there were a hundred centers like this
in denmark
75 in norway and 150 in sweden
where young adults usually in their
early 20s
could spend later on with full state
subsidy
up to six months in order
to find themselves and to develop this
capacity to be a change maker in in
rapidly
changing times and when this was at its
height
10 percent actually of each young
generation
had the opportunity to participate in
one of these
uh six months retreats
and of course that created a critical
mass
in our societies yeah it was quite
interesting to me i mean i
didn't know much about later
scandinavian history yeah we all learned
about the vikings etc
but you know how far down in the league
tables scandinavia was
surprisingly late in the day you know
absolute monarchs
i think the thing that was most shocking
to me was serfdom was not
abolished in denmark to something like
1830. it was like what
here's the most progressive country in
the world probably and it still had
serfdom in the 1830s yeah and that that
was official of abolition in in
in denmark but sort of uh
remains of this serfdom actually existed
in sweden
in the beginning of the 1900s
not official serfdom but that but that
you had part of
the labor force in agriculture
that lived under almost surf like
circumstances that that was up until the
beginning of the 1900s even
it makes the ascent even more amazing
frankly so let's turn to what i believe
is the center of your
argument on how the ascent happened
we'll go and later into a bunch of
interesting fairly idiosyncratic history
of how it happened but
let's start with psychological
development you have a strong section in
the book
on kohlberg keegan etc tell us a little
bit about your thinking
on psychological development and its
role
in you know essentially person making
and society making
yeah and and first i should mention that
i came fairly
late to to the idea of personal
development and understanding personal
uh development i mean the first half of
my business career i
i had no idea about personal development
but it was actually in business
that i started to develop an interest
because
as a chairman of a banking group in
scandinavia i came in contact of course
with leadership development consultants
and organizational consultants who
actually
pointed out that one of the most
important uh
capacities to look for when hiring
top management is really this sort of
inner maturity that makes it possible
for you to
both handle complexity many perspectives
so it's a
matter of cogni cognitive complexity
capacity
but also emotional and relational
uh capacity and and the ability to see
things from different perspectives and
put yourself in another person's
shoes that is always important
in business if not not just only for
instrumental reasons but certainly for
instrumental reasons you are a much
better salesperson if you can actually
take the perspective of of of the buyer
fully and to my surprise these
leadership consultants not only pointed
out the importance of this
but up until that point in life i
thought this was more a function of
intelligence that you were born with
this or not
but they actually showed how this can be
developed and i saw this development
process taking place both in
colleagues of mine and i also myself
participated in some of these activities
and i saw that
wow consciousness development is
actually possible and and
important and important in business and
if we understand this in business why
are we not at all talking about this in
society
why isn't this sort of a major aim in
education
and later on in adult education that
other education should not just be about
learning new facts and new skills
but actually to develop the capacity of
of your of your mind and your heart i
would say
i would say too today so something that
sounded
very sort of new age and intangible
to me certainly became a reality and
when i started to study this a little
bit
again from a perspective of complexity
science
you can really ask yourself the question
if if if
nature through the evolution should
design
sort of this multi-purpose
consciousness multi-purpose mind that we
have
how should nature do that most
efficiently
for humans to be able to live
and adapt in a multitude of different
environments
and of course the answer would be that
nature should do that as nature
usually does in this situation and that
is to
to make complex self-organizing system
and as you know from complexity signs
any
self-organizing complex system given
time
given that it can take in information it
takes in
energy then it can come to these
bifurcation
points where it is possible for the
system
to actually substantially reorganize
into something new and you sometimes
even talk about
emergence and you can have emergent
properties in this
system and then it
isn't that strange that that actually
can happen also
with us humans and again that is what
the german philosophers knew and and
pointed out
and even more interestingly the
theories that schiller and gert and
therefore the scandinavian
politicians and intellectuals had they
correspond as we point out
in the book very closely to
the contemporary academic
models of adult uh
consciousness development and you
mentioned a few that you you mentioned
i mean the the father of this thinking
modern thinking is really piaget
and then you have kolberg and you
mentioned
robert keegan and
the thinking and writings for example of
professor keegan at harvard
is very close to the models that we used
in scandinavia for more than a hundred
years ago
and then you should of course remember
that all
models are wrong so this
phenomenon of consciousness is we are
still
very very early in trying to understand
what's what is going on
so of course as always all models are
wrong
but some are useful and i think
for example the the models of
professor robert keegan points at some
of these
very important developmental steps that
we can take
as adults and the first of those
steps is the same step that schieler and
goethe pointed out
and that is the step of moving away from
what today might be called a socialized
mind
that is dependent on outside
confirmation of our of our values it's
dependent on an outside authority for
guidance in society it's the typical
mind of
of a traditionally religious
person who lives in a religious society
but also a typical
modern person let's call it an
administrative mind with within
a large corporation or something that
takes
the corporate world just for granted and
tries to be the best
possible within that corporate system
without
really questioning the system but then
it is possible
already quite early in life perhaps not
before 25 and for many people this step
doesn't happen until they are 40 or 50
or perhaps
never and that is one of the problems
again professor kegan points out that
in the us according to his estimate at
least half the
population never never leaves this sort
of socialized
mind but it is possible to to leave that
mind and to internalize
and and develop your inner compass and
become what
in keegan's language is self-authoring
and that means that you become in
[Music]
in a very fundamental way a much
much more free to be the author of your
own lives and your own
values and really democracy
as already schiller pointed out
democracy
needs a sufficient amount
of citizens that are actually capable
of thinking for themselves in this
deeper way so in developing
democracy developing the capacity of
self-leadership or self-authoring
capacity
in a large part of population becomes
crucial
yep may be useful at this point to lay
out the five
layers that you guys pulled out of
keegan and
referenced many times in the book
yeah so um i think the the two most
interesting uh levels we've already been
talking about and that is the
the socialized mind and that is the
functioning of
most adolescents and young adults
and in some cases you you remain within
within that
framework of making sense and meaning
for the whole of your life then the next
step
again mentioned as a self-authoring
that's when you can become the author of
your own
values and and author of your life in a
much
deeper way you are not any longer
dependent on
your peer group for um
confirmation and you can actually derive
your own
value from from the from the inside you
have a capacity
to do and say things that is
not appreciated by by your peer group
then later on in life some people
professor keegan points out can even
transcend
this self-authoring mind into something
that he calls
a self-transforming mind and
that involves a capacity to
not only author your own values
but actually take a perspective on that
process and to see
where you are in that process and
actively manage your own process
in that way you also start to see and
this goes back a little bit to this
when we were talking about the socially
constructed
aspect of reality you you also there
start to be able to
take your own culture
as an object up until that point
you your culture or your society or what
some sociologists call your collective
imaginary
and part of the collective imaginary
today is of course
things like money marriage
nation states presidents the market
all of those things that we tend to take
for granted
like the fish takes the water
the fish is swimming in for granted we
start to be able to take this water
as an objective for our reflections
we can start to separate ourselves a
little bit from
our our culture a little bit like
coming back from burning man and
realizing that
wow the world we can construct a
completely different world and live in
that for
for for a week and uh
then coming back to the default reality
you cannot really look at the default
reality with the same
naivety as as before but but that is a
very
very uh rare way of
making meaning and again according to
professor keegan's estimates
we're talking about less than one
percent of the population that that is
uh
making meaning at at that level but even
if
one percent i mean that sounds like a
small number but then again if you're
looking at
the whole of the us for example we are
talking about millions of people
millions of people capable of of could
be 30 million people in theory right
yeah
that's a lot of people well one percent
be three million people yeah what are
the other two
numbers just for our curiosity here yeah
yeah
they are actually identical to
the childhood developmental stages
already
elaborated by pierre scheer so
really as as a newborn you are just in a
fusion with
with your mother you you cannot even
take a perspective of
yourself and you could say that i'm
talking here about
all the time about being able to take
perspectives i i think i should say that
both for piaget
and then for keegan and for other
developmental psychologists
these steps are are really
a transformation where you become
able to take as an object
things that you were previously
in a fusion with for example
as an adult in the socialized mind
you have your values
but you cannot take them as an object
whereas in your your in the transition
to the
self-authoring mind you can much much
more
freely become aware of the fact that
your values are
actually a function of a lot of things
some of which you are actually in
control
of and then in the same way if we go
back to
the child once you left this first
stage where you are in a complete fusion
with your
mother and with with the world you can
start
to perceive yourself as separate from
the world then and then a next step that
usually happens around the
age of five or something like that uh
is the very f which is the stage that
piaget made a bit famous with some of
these experiments
one of which is the experiment where
you have a certain amount of
soft drink in two glasses of the same
shape and then you ask the the child
to uh say which which one of the glasses
the child wants
and then the child says it doesn't
matter because it's equal amount
but then you pour one of the glasses
into a much more narrow
narrow glass or the content of one of
the glasses into a much more narrow
glass
and then all of a sudden it looks much
more
and then typically the three-year-old
child will say well now i want
that glass because there is more in that
one
even though the child actually saw that
it is the same amount
of liquid that was poured over into the
other glass
because a typical three-year-old cannot
take a perspective on
its sense impressions if it looks
more than it is more whereas a child a
few years
older and and typically all or most
seven-year-olds would immediately say
well it's the same
it just looks more but that ability to
take a perspective
on your sense impression does not um
the usual three-year-old have so that is
a very important
also developmental step
and then the next step going into
adolescence you can say that the stages
so far has you have had a very much a
focus on
yourself and your own satisfaction of
your own
needs and of course the young child can
only see his own
needs and if it needs food it will just
cry
and you are very much in this more
egocentric
mind frame up until early adolescence
when you usually go into a more
socialized mind when you realize that
you are actually belonging to a family
or to a group
and what the group thinks about you
all of a sudden becomes important to you
and of course this is a very important
stage of development for
for any person and that is what makes a
civilized society
possible that we are socialized into
this and we
get feelings like shame and we
understand
that our own standing in the group is
very
important on how we think and how we act
and
and all of that and and that is a very
healthy
again developmental stage that we all
need to go through
but that we can then later in life
without completely leaving that we can
still transcend it
and and function on on a more complex
level of
meaning making with a self-authoring
mind
so all of this i mean the amazing thing
is not that we have these models and
again these
all models are just generalizations but
they are helpful and especially in
realizing that we can take these
important steps
also in adulthood and what implication
this has
for our understanding of
society and democracy
and again schiller pointed out so
clearly
that in his mind and he lived through
the french revolution and
he and his fellow philosophers had put
so much
hope into the french revolution and then
they saw
that when the french people got rid of
the king
and they theoretically got this freedom
they were still sort of reaching out for
an authoritarian leader
and first they got robbie speer and then
late to napoleon and and
you have the you had the establishment
on the empire so
why was it not possible for the french
people to really
then develop democracy and schiller
pointed out and the other
german idealist philosophers agreed with
him that
the reason was that not enough many
people in france at that point in time
had actually developed that inner
maturity
to be able to
internalize your source of authority
so the majority or the vast majority was
still looking for an external
authority essentially you're level two
so i mean we talk a lot about
level three and think that's the normal
state but at least the way i read it
i believe your argument was and the
german philosophers picked it up using
different tools
that prior to modernity a lot of people
majority of people were at their level
two essentially like
like a ten-year-old of course they
responded to punishment
and very simple rewards and the real big
transition
to enter modernity was to go from most
people being at
level two to most people being at level
three i.e internalized conformists
bureaucratic mind etc
yeah yeah and absolutely the the the
the the majority but then the argument
is probably that that
in modernity you you need not a majority
to be at a self-authoring level but you
need a critical mass
to do you need a critical mass to be
there
and and what could a critical mass be
well of course
it's always different in different
complex self-organizing system
what what uh constitutes a critical mass
but i would have guessed
5 10 15 20 20
and that the percentage there is
also depending on where in society these
people
are located and the beautiful thing
about this program
of implementing large-scale
consciousness development or large-scale
folk building in
in the scandinavian countries was that
the participants in these programs these
that participated in the program they
came from all
different backgrounds in society
and actually a majority of the
participants were from farming or
working class background and
then perhaps 10 percent is enough if you
have these 10 percent spread out all
over society
if you have 10 in just some isolated
elite
then of course that is not uh enough to
to have
a a tipping impact on on a society so um
yeah it was very clever what what they
did
yeah and again they were kind of feeling
their way
they didn't have the modern
psychological framework but then you go
into
great depth probably more than i was
expecting on the philosophical history
of how these similar concepts were
reached by different means
by a number of philosophers and also
practitioners but you know let's start
with the philosophers
people like shaftesbury and rosso and
kant
and actually one that zack stein talks
about a lot who's been on the show
a couple of times comenius maybe talk a
little bit about how those
earlier you know comedians in shaftsburg
probably before the classic
enlightenment and rosso and kant classic
enlightenment characters
and then and then you have the swiss um
philosopher or pedagogue
also petsalotzi yep i'll come to him
next
but then i'll also go to that
intermediate area the romances
right the gerta crew jenna etc
yeah so not to spend too much time on
the these
early philosophers but we point out
there in in the book that comenius was
probably the first one
of philosophers in europe and he was
from
bohemia from what is today the czech
the czech republic and he was probably
the first one
to in europe to systematically
think through the role of
education and especially the role of
education
in society up until that point education
had been
mostly or only limited to
the elite in the society and once saw
no really so no need to educate them
the masses in in any way and communica
is was one of the first ones to
really understand the importance of of
an educated
population so he had a huge influence on
on the philosophers that came
later he actually spent some time in
sweden
even if he hasn't left very much trace
here in sweden and
he was also active in in holland
but he certainly influenced a lot of
thinkers that came after him and you
mentioned for example
rosso which is also often referred to
also as one of the first
philosophers who has his own philosophy
on
on education that he expressed for
example in works like
emil interestingly enough he never took
any care
and educated any of his own children in
in the
in life but in theory he was interested
in in
education yeah that's always interesting
that
you know he had five kids and he gave
them all away to orphanages right what
the hell
right yeah talk about a guy who does not
walk the walk
right no exactly yep interesting and
then there was the turn
from kind of called high enlightenment
i've always argued that enlightenment
actually had to
fork one down the voltaire dittero
branch and the other down the rousseau
branch towards romanticism
and you focus on the romantic branch and
a lot of interesting things happened
there
you know gerta vikta and a crew of
people who assembled around the
university at jenna
who helped make a transition to one of
the branches
towards you know towards what we have
today but down the romantic branch which
had some good results and some bad
results
i think you can argue the romantic
branch also led to nazism
and marxist leninism but it also led to
some good things so maybe talk just a
little bit because i don't want to get
too bogged down into the philosophers
on how you saw the romantic branch
as the next step in your story yeah
yeah and we already touched
a little bit on on that it of course one
should remember when
one is looking at this part of european
history that
this was before the unification of of
germany so germany was back then a lot
of
small dutches and princeton
and a few kingdoms the kingdom of the
bavaria
kingdom of pricia and gerta
was actually supporting himself as the
prime minister of one of these small
dutches where in which vaimar was the
capital and the second large city in
that little
duchy which is only 20 kilometers away
from weimar
is the old university town of vienna
and um gerta managed to convince
the duke that they should make
the university of jena into a
free thinking university because most of
the universities in
in europe by that time was very much in
under their
religious influence but yena was made
a refuge for free thinkers so that
actually attracted a lot of very high
level
intellectuals and most of these romantic
philosophers or idealist philosophers
they actually spent some time in
in vienna including for example
a little bit later hegel that might be
called the the last of these um series
of
thinkers he actually wrote uh
the final chapter of his
uh magna opus on mind and
society in vienna when napoleon
was fighting the battle
of the which has been called the battle
of jenna just a few kilometers away
he actually won that battle which meant
that he had
more or less defeated germany or or
precia
at least germany was not formed yet
defeated pricia and
hegel knew that the french troops would
come into
iana the day after so he scribbled the
last notes of his manuscript
send it out with a courier and then very
famously he has commented on how he from
a window
saw napoleon come into eni and how he
could see the world
spirit sort of materialized in one
person in in
napoleon there so sorry for that but it
it's an interesting
part of european history and one should
realize that vienna was
its own sort of very uh unique
intellectual
environment and in this environment then
romanticism
was flourishing and why do i find
interesting well it is interesting
because it was
the first really philosophical reaction
against again the enlightenments
or the main focus on the enlightenment
they were different as you pointed out
there were different traits of
enlightenment but the main
focus on reason and science
and the objective world and only the
measurable
and this machine metaphor and
analytics so they were really the first
one that pointed out that this is
yeah this is a very powerful way of
looking at the world and you can do a
lot with
science but we shouldn't forget about
the inner world
and that our inner world follows a
different set of rules and that you
cannot really apply
this strict positivistic thinking in any
meaningful way
on your inner world because i mean you
can't really measure
value and meaning making and purpose
and feelings and all and all of these
things
and one of the main things that they did
was through
introspection really look into this area
of meaning making and cognitive
development
and to make that into a part of
philosophy interesting and it's also
just as in a side note i was always
interested
in these contingencies right history
has some broad themes but there's also
major contingencies what happens if
right if suppose the duke of weimer had
not
listened to gurto i mean which most of
them probably would not have right they
said who is this madman right
and so one person happened to make one
decision which had
really substantial implications for the
rest of
european history and it's i think always
important to remember
the many dots think about your own life
the things that happened in your life
that could have easily gone the other
way or very low probability
and so that's why i thought it was
actually interesting that you got into
this deeper history
than maybe a lot of people would be
interested in the show that
what evolved in scandinavia was
contingent which
i find actually hopeful which means that
we personally can have an effect in the
world today
right gurta and the duke of weimer
together had a huge effect in the world
there's a chance for any of us to
potentially at least have a huge respect
in the world
yeah absolutely and then how these
letters by
by schiller as we develop in the book
how these letters of shilla where he is
explaining
these things even before anything was
published in book form
how they traveled in in both original
and copies
up to denmark and how they influenced
danish philosophers and thinkers like
kirkegaard
and how they then this thinking over the
next
50 years really came to penetrate the
the thinking of most intellectuals in in
scandinavia and it's quite strange then
to to
try to understand that
just 150 years ago in scandinavia we
were actually
all living with a world view that is
quite different
from this modernistic uh
positivistic uh world view that is so
dominant
today in in the western world we
actually had a
quite different outlook on on life and
and the inner world and how that guided
our both
our educational system but also
our view on adult uh development
and then also we should mention that we
also go through in the book
how we then later lost this worldview
we'll come back to that one we'll come
back to that one towards the end
so the next personality want to talk
about someone i had never heard about
johann
pestilosi seemed to have been a talk
about contingent node in history at
least in the story you're telling he
seems to be the guy in which all the
forces combined
and then move back out into the world
tell us just in brief form a little bit
about him and the role he played in this
story
yeah so he he was very much um a
practical
uh pedagogue he he he was a man of
education he
he was a swiss person and
he really wanted to reinvent
learning from from scratch he he was
very much
informed by comenius the czech
philosopher that we
spoke about earlier but he actually
practically
started schools in switzerland mainly
and from the practical experience of
educating young people he
wrote some very influential
writings that were later picked up
and built upon by all these later
philosophers so if you say that comenius
and also you mentioned the
english duke of shaftesbury the third
sorry third earl of chefsbury had also
influenced on these
german thinkers but petsalotzi was the
practical person who actually put this
into real schools
and saw that this was working
and then wrote wrote about it and had a
huge
influence on on education in in europe
and still has
yeah and actually i thought one of the
things that was most interesting about
the story
was the original schools that the first
school league started failed miserably i
think the second one too
and i think this is a very useful point
for people interested in social change
which is theory is good but theory has
to encounter the world
right to be perfected and you can have
all the great ideas in the world you
want but often they're going to be
proven wrong you and i are both
entrepreneurs how often did the business
unfold just the way we wrote it in the
business plan never
absolutely and you need to try and you
need to try again and you need to
understand why things
fails and sometimes of course good
things fail because of of timing or
you're just your business model or
bad luck bad luck or you had a great
idea and a great concept but the market
just didn't want to pay for it
even though it was needed in society so
you couldn't find the finance for it or
whatever
oh yeah all those things have happened
in various companies i've been involved
with right and sometimes we survived and
pivoted and did something else and
sometimes we didn't but yeah so i think
that's a very important one and
certainly in some of the worlds i travel
in there's sometimes gets on my nerve
too much interest in theory right all
right people haven't we talked this song
a bitch to death let's go out and see if
we're right
for instance in the game b world which
i'm involved with pretty heavily
awful lot of theory awful lot of talk
and but i do finally believe with the
community is getting ready to go out and
try some things
i think pestilosi is a perfect example
of how important
taking theory and putting into practice
and then refining it because there's
always things that you get wrong from a
theoretical perspective when it comes to
dealing with the real world
yeah but then we have already been a bit
critical of of the market and we said
that the market is a social construct
and that even the free market i claim
could could be
different so we shouldn't equate
sort of success of an idea of a concept
with
financial success in the present market
because there are
many good ideas i've seen that hasn't
been able to thrive in the market
that has then pivoted or has been
tweaked into something that
is successful in the market but has then
lost the core
idea and is not as good as it could have
been
yeah that's frankly the philosophy and
theory of game b
which is that we have to have completely
different social signaling institutional
structures
if good things are going to survive at a
high rate
and so the two have to co-evolve
together actually three things have to
co-evolve together one are institutional
signaling
second is new ways of self-organizing to
do constructive things in the world not
just top-down hierarchical command and
control
and third ego development people have to
change to be able to operate in a world
like that
and i think those are all there let's
move on to our next topic briefly we're
getting kind of
we've been chatting here a lot we may
have to move it on a little faster here
and that's the kind of surprising but
important nexus that freemasonry
served in all this you talk about later
in the book but i will hop into it here
because a lot of these characters were
masons
yeah yeah so um
[Music]
that's more um that it's not a central
part of of the story of the book but it
is
it is um a thing that we came across
in doing the research too many times to
leave
out of of the uh of the book
the fact that very many of the people
involved in
this uh history were actually freemasons
and
i never myself understood what
freemasons are all about i've never been
a freemason and i haven't understood
at all and certainly it was something
else back then
and what what it is what it is today but
i think that the freemasons actually
back then in
in europe and possibly also in the us
and
as i'm sure you you know many if not all
of the founding fathers of
of the united states constitutions were
freemasons
and somehow they were carrying this sort
of
spirit of uh the possibility
of personal development
and societal development they were
carrying that understanding in some sort
of
practical and ritual way
and becoming part of a freemason lodge
would mean that you would actually enter
a path
of personal development
and i hope i guess and i hope
that the idea that was that this
personal development was not just for
the benefit of yourself or for your
fellow
freemasons but that this personal
development
was actually ultimately for for the good
of
society and i think one can understand
that a bit
from reading the writings of the
founding fathers of the us for example
yeah in fact actually i did when i read
all that in fact i came to the same
conclusion before you had the section in
the book i said hmm this is
an interesting and suspicious pattern
all these freemasons right
and then you made it clear late in the
book and the note i wrote to myself on
my topic sheet was hmm
i wonder what the freemasonry of the
21st century ought to be
yeah maybe talk about that later but now
let's move into kind of where the story
comes into real focus sort of the
creation of the concept of folk building
and how it got started in denmark under
the influence of a thinker named
gruntvig
and a practitioner named christian cold
and others and a bunch of others
yeah yeah and i think this is a typical
case
case study of so what we today would
call
social entrepreneurship so i mean uh
back then and now we're talking
mid-1800s
there were no big governmental decisions
or anything
and again back then all all the
scandinavian countries and certainly
denmark
was absolute monarchies but um
enough many people and
started to uh think about the writings
of these german philosophers that
reached
first denmark and kirkegaard and and his
kierkegaard also has this sort of
developmental view on
our life on how we go through the
different stages
as has nietzsche that was also right
back then harnichi also points out these
steps and he he he talks about how we
are first like a camel
carrying the burden of society and then
you become a lion where you can sort of
more dictate your own life but then
finally the goal of of
any human life is to again become the
child
who sort of is newborn to this process
so these these ideas of lifelong
development were everywhere and
certainly everywhere in denmark and then
we have the pastor
of grundwick who really said let's try
to do something
with with this and he had this school
teacher
cult and they really as social
entrepreneurs they said let's get this
going let's get an old farmhouse and get
the support from some
local farmers and let's try out the
concepts of
how can we do this in in in practice how
can we
help young people really
find their inner compass but but also
help them and we shouldn't forget that
that at this early stage there was also
an emphasis on helping these young
people just all get organized in
in the world learn about their own
history
and their own culture find the cultural
roots in
in society and also later on give them
the
elementary tools for organizing civic
society so these places that were then
called
folk high schools and the whole concept
was called folks building which means
building this german concept of
consciousness
development for the people folks
that's the whole people so it was was
building for for the people and it
started it started very small
but this concept rapidly took on
everyone saw saw the benefits
from this the participants certainly saw
benefits also from a purely
instrumental perspective these young
guys
first it was mostly it was only boys to
start with but
very soon it was both boys and girls men
young men and women
that took place in these folk high
schools they certainly saw that this was
a way of
getting ahead in life perhaps with a
farming background or a working-class
background this was the way
to have an advancement in in
society so it was really a win-win
situation both from society with more
capable lots of more capable citizens
but also from those who participated in
these
folk high schools from an individual
perspective this was
beneficial and then there is so very
soon
this spread to norway and then later to
to a little bit later to sweden it was
implemented in different ways in the
different
countries different people
got in involved and then fairly soon
the governments started to see the
benefits
of these programs and they started to
become subsidized and
in the beginning of of the 1900s then
this was as i said at the beginning you
could spend up to six months at
these faulk high schools with the full
state uh
subsidy and i believe the argument is
that
it was this happenstance lucky break
that these
social entrepreneurs created this idea
of folk high school which
resonated with ordinary people and for a
long while they were paying for it
themselves right
yes yes paying for them themselves but
also as any
social entrepreneur there were also
philanthropists involved
contributings and the local communities
contributing
and they were running again like social
entrepreneurs today
on extremely small budgets
they they were growing their own foods
and very simple accommodations and in
many cases the teachers didn't get paid
or
get paid very very poorly at the start
but yeah they managed and
and then the effect back to the main
theme of the story is that it
raised the participants in their
ego competent you know levels from yeah
level two
level two to level three or from level
three to level four right
yeah and you and you can say i mean in
with contemporary
language that what happened was of
course that you helped a lot more people
to be able to navigate a more complex
world yeah exactly i mean going
going from living in a small farming
village with 80 people and you know
every one of them and all of that
into trying to live into in an urban
industrial
city building and participating in a
democratic
society of course that demands inner
capacities
both cognitive but also emotional and we
might come to the emotional side
a bit later with the expansion of our
circles of belongings
that were very important part of this
concept as well but certainly you you
need
to have more cognitive capacities just
to be able
to to manage and the brilliance here was
really to connect
this individual capacity
to manage and make sense and make
meaning
in the modern world the importance for
the individual
with the importance for society
and that these people knew again already
gertie and shield but certainly also
these
entrepreneurs that brought this to to to
the nordic countries
they knew that if one should be able to
succeed in creating democracy
you need to have as a
citizens you need to have citizens in
those countries
who are actually cognitively and
emotionally
capable of handling democracy
meaning not just think about yourself
and your family
but as actually be able to take a larger
perspective
of what is good for for society as well
yeah and so is it fair to say that in in
your view
having done this research and written
down this story
that perhaps why scandinavia is
different and better at least on many
measures today
is essentially chance that this folk
building concept got going in the 19th
century and
accelerated around 1900 so that earlier
than other places the percentage of
people who had reached the
self-authoring level
of ego development was higher than
elsewhere
yeah absolutely absolutely that that
that's it and you could you referred to
the world value
studies diagram and even if one should
be very careful about
uh equating the the values that you
hold with levels of
inner maturity there is certainly
a a correlation there and
you you could say that these the fact
that we end up in this
extreme corner of the the diagram of the
survey
service survey uh is a fact
of that we have a higher percentage of
people that are making sense of the
world on on a self
authoring level we should we should also
i mean make make clear so that nobody
misunderstands this that
these levels of cognitive development i
mean the
there is certainly a a hierarchy and and
a progression
but it's important to point out that
you are not worth less if you are
on an early stage of the development i
mean
all philosophers and and today
psychologists are very careful in
pointing out that
as with all developments we need to
to be able to crawl before we can walk
before we can run and that each stage
has to take its time but if we are aware
of this
development we could hopefully
create a society
that helps more people earlier in life
reach further in their
maturation process yep we'll talk about
that later
about where we go from here but let's
hop to the thing you just mentioned or
one of the things you mentioned
which is in addition to the five level
model
of ego development you also have a ten
level model
of span and scope of essentially where
one
one's concerns are focused i don't know
if that's quite the right way to
describe it
we call them the circles of belonging
yes
and other writers call the similar
concept circles of concern
okay that's good circles of concern
certainly seems to fit
nicely with what i took away from it do
we want to go through those briefly
or do we just want to talk about them in
a more general sense
yes so um the circles of belonging or
the circles of concern
is an important concept in the way that
again as
small children we very small children we
only care about ourselves and then
when we become a little bit older we
care about our family and our friends
but one of the important thing of course
of becoming an adult
is that you care for your larger
community
and you feel a belonging with your
community and therefore you care for it
and
it is in our genes
which developed of course during stone
age or even before stone age
that we can very naturally relate to and
feel
a belonging to our tribe a number of
people up to perhaps
what some people call the dunbar number
of 100 about 150 people
but if you should go beyond that
and feel not only an intellectual but
actually an
embodied solidarity with a larger
uh group of people and of course back
at the period where we were talking we
were
just mentioning that the nation state of
of germany had not
even been formed in the middle of the
1800s so we were at an age where
the formation of nation states started
to become
important and in a
in a large country like germany or in a
large country which geographically is
even larger sweden
back then there was really no sense of
solidarity or belonging
between someone in bavaria or in prussia
or in the south of sweden and north of
sweden so a big part of this
project was actually to try to expand
the circles of belonging from the family
and the tribe and the village
to actually include all the people in in
the nation
so this was part of the nation building
project
later on but still fairly early in the
beginning of the 1900s
focus shifted and at least in sweden
that focus was very clear
to even go beyond the nation-state
and and to try to extend the circle of
belongings to all of humanity
or even what we might say today you we
need to extend it to
to future uh generations
but the further you try to extend
this these circles of belonging
especially if
if it should be a true embodied feeling
the more inner maturation is demanded
from from you and again you you cannot
skip any stage of
development and this is quite
interesting today where we
try to socialize young people into sort
of feeling a belonging for the whole
human kind without first having
established the more closer circles of
belonging
and then this concept of feeling a
solidarity for the whole of humanity if
that is not
really grounded in a developmental
process but just
sort of you are socialized into that
then that can
very very easily disappear and i think
that is what we are seeing in many of
the nationalists
movements today anywhere in in the world
that
for many people this sort of solidarity
with the whole of the world is we carry
that
very very lightly and we can easily
revert back to
only thinking about our our family or
our closer
circles yeah that was one of the things
i took you know
my eyebrow one up when i read how
important nationalism
was in this story many of us sort of are
ambivalent about nationalism but i think
you made this strong point that it was
actually a step of maturity up from
you know the manor and the market town
that you live near and maybe your church
yeah and you should know that in canada
in germany back then
these different small dutches they were
actually at war
with each other and and the kin kingdom
of bavaria and the kingdom of prussia
were arch enemies and the same i mean
sweden and denmark has always been
enemies and and in wars with
each other so we were living in a
different world where
just taking the step from the this very
closer
circle of just being uh
belonging to to just your tribe in the
south of sweden to actually caring for
old swedes that was a huge step
and it was a step in the right direction
back then
today nationalism is a step backwards
it's a step
back in the evolutionary stage when it
comes to society
but when we are not making this
connection
between the societal development and our
own personal development
then we can't really see what is going
on with these
new nationalistic tendencies in
in europe and everything and if you can
connect
this to the personal development of
people in the country then it becomes
more clear what
what is going on and also realizing that
in times of
rapid social change it is the natural
default of us humans
to look for an authoritarian outside
source for security and protection
and if we do not want to do that then we
will have to work
on ourselves and also help other people
to
to develop and mature very good
i'm going to skip over an interesting
section but not really on the main
lineless story which is where you
validate your argument by comparing
what happened in finland germany and
nordic immigrants to the united states
and some others
i'm going to mention just one out of
that section which i thought was
particularly interesting and again an
eyebrow razor
you made the very interesting point that
the nordic immigrants to the united
states are well known for having
been relatively easily digested had
relatively few problems
low crime rates you know very
self-sufficient etc
and then you pointed out that those
nordic immigrants came to the u.s
well before the establishment of the
welfare state
in scandinavia so whatever capabilities
and characters they had
predated the welfare state and you
pointed out to i thought a very
interesting and important one that's
often lost
especially in so-called progressive
circles that
a responsibility may have actually been
the superpower
that the nordic peoples had at that time
can you say a little bit about that
absolutely i mean a very important
part of this process of of maturation
or ego development or what you would
like to call it
is that with this development you become
aware
of more things in yourself and in your
environment and as you become aware of
them and you are capable of taking them
as
objects of of reflection whereas before
you might not even have been aware of
them
the these things had you rather than you
having them
as developmental psychologists says and
perhaps i should have
mentioned this example earlier but
one very clear way of looking at this is
of course like
like a young child who is angry
then the anger has the child
the child cannot relate to the anger the
anger has
the child whereas an adult hopefully
a mature adult can have the anger
rather than the anger having the person
and you can look at the anger and you
can think what should i do with it
should i
should i repress it or should is this a
healthy
opportunity to actually let out a bit of
anger in this process you can take that
as an object you can have your anger
rather than your anger having you
so in this process on various levels
when when you can take as an
object more and more things both inside
you and also in
society with that comes a freedom of
course
and and and the extended freedom that
that is why
you can really talk about a hierarchy of
development
because each steps actually contains the
earlier ones
but increases your freedom you can see
more and you can relate to more
but then of course with that comes a
larger responsibility
so with a how healthy adult development
and with a healthy
developmental process and also relating
this to the circles of belonging where
you become aware of
you belong into larger and larger
circles you also with this belonging
feel a responsibility so this
process of what was taking place at the
folk high schools was certainly
developing your freedom
but with that developing your ability to
take
responsibility and of course that is a
very very important
capacity in any society and of course in
in the early days of the uh american
society when you came as a settler
almost alone out in nature you claimed
virgin territory in minnesota for your
family and all of that
then of course your ability to take
responsibility
was a very important capacity yeah and
unfortunately a lot of particularly
progressives in the united states at
least
forget the responsibility piece right
they
don't want to point the finger at people
for not taking responsibility
and and i think probably that goes back
to the fact that people weren't educated
in a way like your folk bildong that
included both capability and
responsibility
yeah because if i should defend the
progressives now if if you don't have
this
model of development and and
also if you have a lot of people in
society
that are not at a level of maturation
where they actually have the capacity to
take responsibility
then it doesn't matter i mean how much
responsibility you put on them
they will not be able to take the
responsibility
because they do not even see
the problem that they should take
responsibility for
so they are perhaps then the
progressives are might be right then in
certain situations
just trying to put responsibility to
people is
is not the way forward but where they go
wrong then
is that they do not talk at all about
the responsibility the right way to go
is to say
well for this society to function then
we need to
help as many people as possible to reach
that level of inner capacity
where you are capable of taking
responsibility so let's help
people to reach that level so that they
are capable of taking responsibility
and then making sure that they do take
responsibility
or something in that direction i think
that's good though i would point out
that
prior to education being general at all
like here on the american pioneers where
i'm living now
our farm was settled in 1746
by you know a guy with a mule and an axe
and a chicken maybe and one and one or
two rifles
and they knew how to take responsibility
nobody had to teach them i mean it was
the natural state of the world
yeah yeah but but you know again that
that environment
is is probably very supportive of
development
because if you do not develop yourself
in that environment either
you just become a third-ranked person in
a gang or something
or you develop an ability to take
responsibility and
and and you mature so i think sad to say
but a hash
environment is really an environment
where you either
do develop or or uh or or not
or in the pioneer days you just died
right if you're if you couldn't grow
crops for a couple of years you were
gone
i just want to say one one more thing on
that and looking at the developmental
level of course you you can
force some sort of responsibility
through just physical violence and if
you go back in medieval ages or or
whatever i mean if
if if you don't comply and do and in
some sort of take responsibility then we
will flog you
and you can do something like that but
real responsibility
has to come from from the inside and
that is when you
really take responsibility and again
build building a modern democracy that
is
not dependent on on violence for it to
function
then you need to develop this inner
capacity to take
responsibility well i think that makes
perfect sense
we're getting really short on time here
unfortunately so many interesting topics
we could talk about
so in the last 12 minutes or 10 minutes
or so i'd like to
have you talk a little bit about a
section you have in the book on how
the binding energy of bildung is
unraveling in scandinavia today
and what might be done about it what
might a bildong
3.0 look like to help ratchet
first scandinavia and then europe and
then humanity more generally
to the next level yeah yeah
just want to mention two things
that i don't want us to skip over one is
a question a very natural question so
why didn't this work in in germany
and and the very very simple answer
there is that
yeah all these philosophers came from
from germany
the the leaders in in germany fully
realized the potential of
building but due to the
civil unrest in europe during the middle
of the
1800s in 1848 there were revolutions in
frankfurt and in berlin
the authorities in berlin lost control
over berlin to the workers
to the revolting workers for three days
in 48
so the politicians there said building
and consciousness development
is great let's give it to our sons
because back then it was only the suns
but we should never give this
possibility to the workers because that
will only lead to revolution
so there was no folk build on but the
universities were certainly
formed on this then after the first
world war we had the
weak weimar republic and then more and
more people in germany started to
realize that in order to get this weak
republic to work we might need to give
building to
to the people and there were actually
efforts in that direction
in 28 and in the late of the 20s
but then of course already in 32
the demand for a strong leader had
reached the level that
hitler was able to to grab power in in
germany so
too little building too late in in
germany
that's the the answer to why this didn't
happen in
in germany but we rather had the
opposite development there
then in scandinavia so why are we losing
it in scandinavia well
after the fact that that germany lost to
a world
wars everything german became suspicious
and we stopped having german as the main
academic language we stopped reading the
german philosophers
and we all turned towards the
anglo-saxon world we talked
turned toward oxford and cambridge and
harwood and there
of course it was that still the teaching
of
loki and the scar and the enlightenment
thinking of
our mind as a rational machine and in
the economics department it was all
about human
economics so we actually forgot about
the importance of
inner consciousness development and
adapted this
homo economics picture of of humans and
we shouldn't put all the blame on on the
anglo-saxon philosophers we
we actually in sweden were amongst
the most strong proponents of
positivism in during the 1900s meaning
that
only the philosophy stating that only
what is
measurable really counts and that the
inner world our subjective world is
too suspicious really to really be
dealing with in serious terms in in
philosophy
so today in scandinavia we are all
focused on this sort of
outer measurable world and we are all
with the pisa reports and
doing statistics on learning facts and
things like that
and the building component disappeared
during the 50s and 60s
and i think that in the 70s and 80s and
perhaps even 90s that were still
teachers that were themselves
raised in in a building a conscious
world but now not even the teachers know
anything about this so
this is really a secret even
to us in scandinavia and when we write
our political and intellectual
history this is not really
remembered and what got lynn and myself
actually
starting the research into this was that
we we
found a newspaper article from 1889
by one of the founding fathers of the
modern
swedish democracy called the alma
branting
where he he wrote something along the
lines that
we social democrats have been all too
much focused
on the material aspects of life
they are certainly necessary but they
are just a prerequisite
for the inner development
and that the main task is to bring
humanity to a new developmental level
and we had never heard about these sort
of
perspectives by reading the contemporary
books on political history in sweden so
that that was really
an eye opener for us and the starting
point for for the research
and the writing okay so they so the
scandinavians have forgotten
their secret ingredient yeah that
happened by chance more or less
right okay so now what do we do going
forward what's
folk build on 3.0 look like to you
yeah okay so i i i sometimes say
that that i don't see the nordic secret
as a blueprint i don't think that
we should do this again
but it's not a blueprint but it's
certainly a case study
in the way that if we today are
are talking about the need for
broad-scale
consciousness development developing our
inner capabilities to handle a more
complex world this is not just some new
age
talk this is actually something that has
been tried
fairly independently in three different
countries
full scale trials and they turned out
successfully so we should see this as a
case study that
focusing on on developing inner
capacities to handle the demo
the challenges of our modern world and
democracy has actually
worked and then the question becomes how
would one do it
today and and i don't know
i honestly don't know but i think it's a
starting point
is really to to again change
our world view and leave the idea that
our
our minds are a computer or a machine
and really start looking at our mind as
these complex
evolving organic systems that are
capable of not only learning
but also evolving in in depth and and
nuance
and if you if you have that perspective
then of course you realize that in this
rapidly moving world today where we do
not know what the world will look like
in 20 years perhaps not even
10 years it's so difficult to to
say what should we teach our young
people in in in school and at uni
university
well of course reading and and and
writing and
arithmetics will always be be
a fundament of learning but on top of
that i mean even today when you start at
google or at a tech firm
what you learned at university just
three years earlier is
old news you have to be constantly
learning
so then to focus our education and
certainly our higher education and our
lifelong
education at developing these sort of
inner
capacities of complexity
and being able to take more perspectives
see the world in more depth and and and
nuance will be the key both
for your own individual personal success
in in the uh
work market to tomorrow you will need
this flex inner flexibility and capacity
just to stay alive in in the workforce
in the future
but it will also be a key asset
to uh be able to
develop our democracies in into a next
level where we can
actually where we are actually able of
some sort of collective sense making
even as the world becomes more and more
complex
around us and exactly how to do this how
to
implement this i don't know certainly
you cannot just do this through teaching
you have to have
immersive learning perhaps we should
give young people the possibility
in their 20s to take half a year to
go into some sort of immersive learning
and personal
development if that is too much we might
use technology to support this
in a developmental project and my
foundation in
stockholm is active together with
another foundation in stockholm called
the
northwind foundation in developing
a non-profit open source co-created
digital platform
for personal inner growth called 29k
where we have interventions
but also these video sharing movements
where you can really
integrate and deepen your inner growth
and again i'm not suggesting that we are
replacing in personal meetings with
digital platforms and video conferencing
but certainly if we are going to reach
millions and millions of people with the
possibilities of
inner lifelong development we need to
democratize this in some way and
i believe that technology could
certainly be a
one helping resource in in that
respect very good i think at that we
will
end it here it's been a fabulous
conversation i strongly recommend
the book the nordic secret if you want
to get into this in in more detail and i
think you
are pointing one of the important ways
forward we really do have to
think hard about who we are as people
with some volition
and who we want our children to be to
create the kind of society that we want
that's really the bottom line yeah and
can i also
end by doing a bit of promotion for my
latest book it's called the world
we create and that is about becoming
conscious about this
social imaginary collective imaginary
that we are living in and
how this personal inner development and
societal change goes hand in hand
thank you very much jim
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com